I'd like to talk a little bit this morning
أود التحدث قليلا هذا الصباح
about what happens if we move from design
عما سيحدث اذا ما انتقلنا من التصميم
to design thinking.
الى "التفكير التصميمي"
Now this rather old photo up there
هذه الصورة هنا
is actually the first project I was ever hired to do,
هي لأول مشروع عملت عليه
something like 25 years ago.
قبل 25 عاما
It's a woodworking machine, or at least a piece of one,
انها آلة لصناعة المشغولات الخشبية, أو على الأقل جزء من الألة
and my task was to
أما مهمتي فكانت
make this thing a little bit more modern,
أن أحولها الى آلة أكثر حداثة
a little bit easier to use.
وأسهل في الأستخدام
I thought, at the time, I did a pretty good job.
اعتقدت أنذاك, أنني قمت بعمل جيد.
Unfortunately, not very long afterwards
ولكن بعد فترة قصيرة , ولسوء الحظ,
the company went out of business.
فقد أعلنت الشركة افلاسها.
This is the second project that I did. It's a fax machine.
هذا هو المشروع الثاني الذي عملت عليه. جهاز فاكس
I put an attractive shell around some new technology.
لقد وضعت غلافا جذابا حول تقنية جديدة
Again, 18 months later,
ومرة أخرى, بعد 18 شهرا
the product was obsolete.
أصبح المنتج قديم الطراز
And now, of course, the whole technology is obsolete.
أما الأن, بالطبع, فحتى تقنية الفاكس أصبحت قديمة الطراز.
Now, I'm a fairly slow learner,
صحيح أنني بطيء التعلم قليلا
but eventually it occurred to me that
ولكن في نهاية المطاف بدأت أفكر
maybe what passed for design
أن ما حدث للتصميم, ربما
wasn't all that important --
لم يكن بتلك الأهمية.
making things more attractive,
جعل المنتجات أكثر جاذبية,
making them a bit easier to use,
وأسهل للأستخدام,
making them more marketable.
وأكثر قابلية للتسويق.
By focusing on a design,
من خلال التركيز على تصميم واحد
maybe just a single product,
وربما منتج واحد,
I was being incremental
فقد كنت أفكر بشكل متدرج
and not having much of an impact.
ولم أكن ذو تأثير كبير
But I think this small view of design
باعتقادي أن هذه النظرة الضيقة للتصميم
is a relatively recent phenomenon,
هي ظاهرة حديثة نسبيا
and in fact really emerged
وقد برزت
in the latter half of the 20th century
في النصف الأخير من القرن العشرين
as design became a tool of consumerism.
حين أصبح التصميم أداة استهلاكية
So when we talk about design today,
لذلك فإننا عندما نتكلم عن التصميم, هذه الأيام,
and particularly when we read about it in the popular press,
وتحديدا عندما نقرأ عنه في الصحف والأعلام,
we're often talking about products like these.
فاننا نجد منتجات مثل هذه !
Amusing? Yes. Desirable? Maybe.
مسلية؟ نعم... جذابة؟ ربما.
Important? Not so very.
مفيدة؟ ليس كثيرا
But this wasn't always the way.
ولكن التصميم لم يكن هكذا دائما.
And I'd like to suggest that if we take
لذلك أقترح أن ننظر للأمور
a different view of design,
من زاوية أخرى
and focus less on the object
ولنركز بشكل أقل على المنتج
and more on design thinking as an approach,
وبشكل أكبر على التفكير التصميمي كنهج,
that we actually might see the result in a bigger impact.
عندها يمكن أن يكون تأثيرنا أكبر.
Now this gentleman, Isambard Kingdom Brunel,
هذا الرجل العظيم, "إزامبارد كنغدوم برونيل",
designed many great things in his career in the 19th century,
صمم العديد من الأشياء العظيمة في مسيرته المهنية, في القرن التاسع عشر
including the Clifton suspension bridge in Bristol
مثل جسر كليفتون المعلق في "بريستول"
and the Thames tunnel at Rotherhithe.
ونفق التايمز في "روذرهيذ"
Both great designs and actually very innovative too.
وكلا التصميمين عظيمين, وعلى درجة عالية من الابداع.
His greatest creation
أما انجازه الأكبر
runs actually right through here in Oxford.
فيمر هنا عبر أكسفورد
It's called the Great Western Railway.
وهي "شبكة السكك الحديدية الغربية العظمى" في المملكة المتحدة
And as a kid I grew up very close to here,
وقد أمضيت طفولتي في جوار أكسفورد
and one of my favorite things to do
وأحدى هواياتي المفضلة كانت
was to cycle along by the side of the railway
أن أتنزه بدراجتي بجوار هذه السكة الحديدية
waiting for the great big express trains to roar past.
بانتظار سماع هدير القطار
You can see it represented here in J.M.W. Turner's painting,
يمكنكم رؤية ذلك في لوحة جيه.إم.دبليو تورنر
"Rain, Steam and Speed".
"قطار, دخان وسرعة"
Now, what Brunel said that he wanted to achieve for his passengers
أراد برونل ان يعطي للمسافرين
was the experience of floating across the countryside.
الانطباع بالعوم في الريف البريطاني
Now, this was back in the 19th century.
هذا كان في القرن التاسع عشر !
And to do that meant creating the flattest gradients
وكان لا بد من بناء المسار الأكثر انبساطا
that had ever yet been made,
في ذلك الزمان
which meant building long viaducts across river valleys --
مما أدى الى بناء جسور ضخمة في وديان الأنهار
this is actually the viaduct across the Thames at Maidenhead --
هذا الجسر على نهر التايمز في "ميدينهيد"
and long tunnels such as the one at Box, in Wiltshire.
والى بناء أنفاق طويلة مثل النفق تحت نهر "البوكس", في "ويلتاشير"
But he didn't stop there. He didn't stop
ولكن "برونل" لم يكتف بذلك... لم يكتف
with just trying to design the best railway journey.
فقط بتصميم أفضل رحلة على متن قطار
He imagined an integrated transportation system
وانما وضع تصورا لنظام نقل متكامل
in which it would be possible for a passenger to embark
حيث بامكان المسافر ركوب
on a train in London
القطار في لندن
and disembark from a ship in New York.
والنزول من سفينة في نيويورك
One journey from London to New York.
رحلة واحدة من لندن الى نيويورك
This is the S.S. Great Western that he built
هذه صورة للسفينة "س.س غرايت وسترن" التي بناها
to take care of the second half of that journey.
لتؤمن النصف الثاني من هذه الرحلة.
Now, Brunel was working 100 years before
أعمال برونل هذه, كانت قبل 100 عام
the emergence of the design profession,
من ظهور التصميم كمهنة
but I think he was using design thinking
ولكني أعتقد أنه كان يستعمل "التفكير التصميمي"
to solve problems and to create world-changing innovations.
لحل المشكلات, ولتقديم ابتكارات قد تغير العالم
Now, design thinking begins with what Roger Martin,
"التفكير التصميمي" بدأ مع روجر مارتن,
the business school professor at the University of Toronto,
(أستاذ كلية التجارة في جامعة تورنتو)
calls integrative thinking.
الذي أطلق عليه اسم "التفكير التكاملي"
And that's the ability to exploit opposing ideas
وهو القدرة على استعمال الأفكار المتعارضة
and opposing constraints
والرغبات المتعارضة
to create new solutions.
لخلق حلول جديدة.
In the case of design, that means
في حالة التصميم, ذلك يعني
balancing desirability, what humans need,
اقامة التوازن بين الرغبة و الحاجة الانسانية
with technical feasibility,
وبين الجدوى التقنية
and economic viability.
والجدوى الاقتصادية.
With innovations like the Great Western,
بفضل ابتكارات كالغرب الأعظم,
we can stretch that balance to the absolute limit.
بامكاننا الوصول بهذا التوازن للحدود القصوى.
So somehow, we went from this to this.
بطريقة أو بأخرى, انتقلنا من هنا الى هنا
Systems thinkers who were reinventing the world,
من المفكرين والمبدعين الذين كانوا يحاولون اعادة تشكيل العالم,
to a priesthood of folks in black turtlenecks and designer glasses
الى طائفة من أشخاص يرتدون بلوزا سوداء ونظارات على الموضة
working on small things.
ويعملون على أشياء صغيرة.
As our industrial society matured,
مع نضوج مجتمعنا الصناعي
so design became a profession
تحول التصميم الى مهنة
and it focused on an ever smaller canvas
تركز على مشاريع صغيرة
until it came to stand for aesthetics,
حتى انتهى به المطاف على التركيز على الجمال
image and fashion.
الصورة والموضة.
Now I'm not trying to throw stones here.
أنا لا أحاول ان أنتقد أحدا هنا
I'm a fully paid-up member of that priesthood,
حتى أنني عضو في طائفة المصممين الحديثين
and somewhere in here I have my designer glasses.
ولدي نظاراتي "اخر موضة" في مكان ما هنا
There we go.
ها هي.
But I do think that perhaps design
ولكني أعتقد أن التصميم
is getting big again.
عاد ليهتم بالشؤون الكبرى
And that's happening through
وهذا التحول يتم
the application of design thinking
عبر تطبيق "التفكير التصميمي"
to new kinds of problems --
على معضلات جديدة --
to global warming, to education,
الإحتباس الحراري, التعليم
healthcare, security, clean water, whatever.
العناية الصحية, الأمن, تأمين المياه النظيفة, وغيرها.
And as we see this reemergence of design thinking
أننا نشهد انبعاث "التفكير التصميمي"
and we see it beginning to tackle new kinds of problems,
ومعالجته للمعضلات المستجدة
there are some basic ideas that I think we can observe that are useful.
هناك بعض الأفكار التي بامكاننا مراقبتها والتي توضح هذا التحول
And I'd like to talk about some of those
وسوف أعرض عليكم بعض هذه الأفكار
just for the next few minutes.
خلال الدقائق القادمة
The first of those is that design is
أول هذه الأفكار هو أن محور التصميم
human-centered.
هو الإنسان
It may integrate technology and economics,
يمكن للتصميم أن يدمج التقنية والأقتصاد
but it starts with what humans need, or might need.
ولكنه يبدأ دائما من حاجة الأنسان, أو مما يمكن أن يحتاجه
What makes life easier, more enjoyable?
كيف تصبح الحياة أسهل, وأكثر متعة؟
What makes technology useful and usable?
كيف تصبح التقنية مفيدة وسهلة الأستعمال؟
But that is more than simply good ergonomics,
كل ذلك أكبر من مجرد غلاف جذاب
putting the buttons in the right place.
أو وضع الأزرار في المكان المناسب
It's often about understanding culture and context
وانما يجب فهم الحضارة والسياق
before we even know where to start to have ideas.
قبل أن نبدأ بأعطاء أفكار جديدة.
So when a team was working on a new vision screening program in India,
فمثلا عندما بدأ فريق طبي يعمل على برنامج جديد لفحص النظر في الهند,
they wanted to understand what the aspirations
أرادوا فهم تطلعات
and motivations were of these school children
ودوافع تلاميذ المدارس
to understand how they might play a role
ليجدوا الطريقة الأمثل لكي يتمكنوا من
in screening their parents.
فحص أهالي التلاميذ
Conversion Sound has developed a high quality,
"كونفيرجن ساوندز" (الفريق الطبي أعلاه) طورت
ultra-low-cost digital hearing aid
أجهزة مساعادات رقمية للسمع منخفضة التكلفة ولكن ذات نوعية عالية
for the developing world.
موجهة للعالم النامي.
Now, in the West we rely on highly trained technicians
في الغرب نعتمد على تقنيين على درجة عالية من التدريب
to fit these hearing aids.
لتصنيع هذه الأجهزة.
In places like India, those technicians simply don't exist.
في دول مثل الهند,هؤلاء التقنيين غير متوفرين
So it took a team working in India
لذلك فأن فريق العمل في الهند
with patients and community health workers
عمل مع المرضى والعاملين في المجال الصحي
to understand how a PDA
ليدرك كيف يمكن لمساعد رقمي شخصي
and an application on a PDA
ولتطبيقاته
might replace those technicians
أن يستبدلوا هؤلاء التقنيين
in a fitting and diagnostic service.
في تأمين التشخيص المناسب.
Instead of starting with technology,
بدلا من البدأ بالتكنولوجية
the team started with people and culture.
فان فريق العمل استند الى الشعب والى الحضارة الهندية.
So if human need is the place to start,
فعندما تكون الحاجة الأنسانية هي نقطة البداية
then design thinking rapidly moves on to
فان "التفكير التصميمي" يتحول الى
learning by making.
التعلم عبر التطبيق.
Instead of thinking about what to build,
فبدل أن نفكر ماذا نبني,
building in order to think.
علينا أن نبني لنفكر.
Now, prototypes speed up the process of innovation,
في وقتنا الحاضر, النماذج الأولية تساعد في تسريع عملية الأبتكار
because it is only when we put our ideas out into the world
لانه, وفقط عندما نطبق أفكارنا في العالم
that we really start to understand their strengths and weaknesses.
بإستطاعتنا أن ندرس نقاط القوة والضعف فيها
And the faster we do that,
وكلما أسرعنا في التطبيق
the faster our ideas evolve.
فان أفكارنا تتطور بسرعة.
Now, much has been said and written about
لقد قيل وكتب الكثير عن
the Aravind Eye Institute in Madurai, India.
معهد "أرافيند" للعيون في "مادوراي", في الهند
They do an incredible job of serving very poor patients
أنهم يقومون بعمل رائع, بتطبيب المرضى المعدمين
by taking the revenues from those who can afford to pay
بفضل الأرباح التي يحققونها من المرضى الذين بامكانهم الدفع
to cross-subsidize those who cannot.
يعالجون المرضى الفقراء.
Now, they are very efficient,
طريقتهم فعالة جدا,
but they are also very innovative.
ولكنهم ايضا مبدعون.
When I visited them a few years ago,
عندما زرت المعهد منذ بضعة سنوات
what really impressed me was their willingness
لفت انتباهي رغبتهم
to prototype their ideas very early.
بانتاج النماذج الأولية مبكرا.
This is the manufacturing facility
هذه صورة لمرفق تصنيع
for one of their biggest cost breakthroughs.
يمثل أحدى أهم الأختراقات لتخفيض تكلفة الأنتاج.
They make their own intraocular lenses.
أنهم يصنعون العدسات الطبية بأنفسهم
These are the lenses that replace those
هذه العدسات ستستبدل تلك التي
that are damaged by cataracts.
أتلفها مرض الماء الأبيض (مرض يصيب عدسة العين)
And I think it's partly their prototyping mentality
واعتقد أن اعتمادهم الأنمذجة (تحضير النماذج الأولية)
that really allowed them to achieve the breakthrough.
قد ساعدهم على تحقيق هذا الأختراق
Because they brought the cost down
لأنهم تمكنوا من تخفيض التكلفة
from $200 a pair,
من 200 دولار لزوج العدسات
down to just $4 a pair.
الى 4 دولارات فقط.
Partly they did this by instead of building
وقد ساعدهم في ذلك, الى حد ما, أنهم بدلا من أن يبنوا
a fancy new factory,
مصنعا جديدا باهظ التكاليف,
they used the basement of one of their hospitals.
قد استمعلوا الطابق الأرضي في أحد مستشفياتهم
And instead of installing the large-scale machines
وبدل ان يستعملوا الألات الضخمة
used by western producers,
التي يستعملها نظرائهم الغربيون
they used low-cost CAD/CAM prototyping technology.
استعملوا تقنيات التصميم بمساعدة الكمبيوتر.
They are now the biggest manufacturer of these lenses in the developing world
انهم الأن أكبر مصنع للعدسات الطبية في العالم النامي
and have recently moved into a custom factory.
وقد تمكنوا مؤخرا من الأنتقال الى مصنع خاص بهم.
So if human need is the place to start,
لذلك فعندما تكون الحاجة الأنسانية هي نقطة الأنطلاق
and prototyping, a vehicle for progress,
وتقنيات الأنمذجة, وسيلة للتقدم
then there are also some questions to ask about the destination.
يبقى هناك عدد من الأسئلة حول الغاية
Instead of seeing its primary objective as consumption,
فبدلا من اتخاذ الأستهلاك غاية أولى
design thinking is beginning to explore the potential of participation --
فأن "التفكير التصميمي" بدأ يستكشف احتمالات المشاركة والمساهمة
the shift from a passive relationship
النقلة من علاقة سلبية
between consumer and producer
بين المستهلك والمنتج
to the active engagement of everyone
الى مشاركة فاعلة من الجميع
in experiences that are meaningful,
في التجارب المعبرة,
productive and profitable.
المنتجة والمثمرة.
So I'd like to take the idea that Rory Sutherland talked about,
لذلك أود أن أخذ الفكرة التي تحدث عنها "روري سوزرلاند",
this notion that intangible things are worth perhaps more than physical things,
نظرية أن الأشياء المعنوية قد تكون أكثر قيمة من الأشياء المادية,
and take that a little bit further and say that
أود أن أخذها وأضيف عليها
I think the design of participatory systems,
أنني أظن أن تصميم أنظمة متعاونة
in which many more forms of value
حيث هناك أكثر من معيار للقيمة
beyond simply cash
أبعد من القيمة المادية المباشرة
are both created and measured,
وحيث بامكاننا خلق وقياس هذه المعايير
is going to be the major theme, not only for design,
سيكون موضوعا أساسيا, ليس فقط للتصميم,
but also for our economy as we go forward.
وانما أيضا لإقتصادنا في تطورنا ونحن نمضي قدما.
So William Beveridge, when he wrote the first of his famous reports in 1942,
وعندما كتب "ويليام بيفريدج" أول تقاريره الشهيرة في عام 1942,
created what became Britain's welfare state
أسس ما سيعرف لاحقا بدولة الرعاية الإجتماعية في بريطانيا
in which he hoped that every citizen
حيث تمنى أن يكون كل مواطن
would be an active participant
مشاركا فعالا
in their own social well-being.
في تحقيق الصالح الأجتماعي.
By the time he wrote his third report,
في الوقت الذي انتهى فيه من كتابة تقريره الثالث,
he confessed that he had failed
أقر بفشله
and instead had created a society of welfare consumers.
وبأنه أسس مجتمعا من مستهلكي الرعاية الأجتماعية.
Hilary Cottam, Charlie Leadbeater,
هيلاري كوتام, تشارلي لدباتر,
and Hugo Manassei of Participle
و هيوغو ماناسي أوف بارتيسيبل
have taken this idea of participation,
أخذوا فكرة ويليام بيفريدج حول المشاركة,
and in their manifesto entitled Beveridge 4.0,
وفي كتابهم المعنون" بيفريدج 4.0",
they are suggesting a framework
يقترحون ألية عمل
for reinventing the welfare state.
لتجديد دولة الرعاية الأجتماعية.
So in one of their projects called Southwark Circle,
وفي أحد مشاريعهم المسمى دائرة ساوثوورك
they worked with residents in Southwark, South London
عملوا مع السكان في ساوثوورك, جنوبي لندن
and a small team of designers
ومع مجموعة صغيرة من المصممين
to develop a new membership organization
لتطوير هيئة جديدة
to help the elderly with household tasks.
لمساعدة كبار السن في المهام المنزلية.
Designs were refined and developed
التصاميم طورت وصقلت
with 150 older people and their families
مع 150 عجوز وعائلاتهم
before the service was launched earlier this year.
وذلك قبل أطلاق المشروع في وقت سابق من هذا العام
We can take this idea of participation
لعله بإمكاننا ان ناخذ فكرة المشاركة هذه
perhaps to its logical conclusion
الى خلاصتها المنطقية
and say that design may have its greatest impact
والقول انه يمكن للتصميم ان يكون له التأثير الاكبر
when it's taken out of the hands of designers
عندما ينتقل من يد المصميمين
and put into the hands of everyone.
الى يد الجميع
Nurses and practitioners at U.S. healthcare system
الممرضات والأطباء في نظام العناية الصحية الاميركي
Kaiser Permanente
ًكايسر برماننتً
study the topic of improving the patient experience,
يدرسون كيفية تحسين تجربة المريض
and particularly focused on the way that they exchange knowledge
بالتركيز خصوصا على طريقة تبادلهم للمعلومات حول المريض
and change shift.
وتغيير المناوبات
Through a program of observational research,
عبر برنامج يقوم على البحث والمراقبة,
brainstorming new solutions and rapid prototyping,
تجميع الإقتراحات الجديدة وخلق النماذج بسرعة.
they've developed a completely new way to change shift.
طوروا أسلوبا جديدا لتغيير المناوبات.
They went from retreating to the nurse's station
فبدلا من الذهاب الى غرفة الممرضات
to discuss the various states and needs of patients,
أصبحوا يناقشون حالة المرضى وحاجاتهم,
to developing a system that happened on the ward
عبر استعمال نظام مستحدث في غرفة المريض
in front of patients, using a simple software tool.
وبحضوره, وذلك بفضل برمجية بسيطة.
By doing this they brought the time that they were away from patients
بفضل هذه الطريقة, نجحوا في تقليص وقت غيابهم عن المرضى
down from 40 minutes to 12 minutes, on average.
من 40 دقيقة لـ 20 دقيقة, كمعدل.
They increased patient confidence and nurse happiness.
وعززوا ثقة المرضى وراحة الممرض(ة)
When you multiply that by all the nurses
وعندما تحسب ذلك على كل الممرضين
in all the wards in 40 hospitals in the system,
في كل الأجنحة في 40 مستشفى طبق هذا النظام
it resulted, actually, in a pretty big impact.
ونتج عن ذلك, أن هناك تأثير كبير
And this is just one of thousands
هذه واحدة فقط من الاف
of opportunities in healthcare alone.
الفرص المتوفرة في مجال العناية الصحية وحده.
So these are just some of the kind of basic ideas
هذه فقط مجموعة أمثلة من التطبيقات
around design thinking
حول "التفكير التصميمي"
and some of the new kinds of projects
وبعض المشاريع الجديدة
that they're being applied to.
التي طبقت عليها.
But I'd like to go back to Brunel here,
ولكنني أود العودة للحديث عن "برونل" هنا,
and suggest a connection that might explain why this is happening now,
وسوف أقترح رؤيتي لماذا يحصل هذا التحول الان,
and maybe why design thinking is a useful tool.
ولماذا "التفكير التصميمي" هو أداة مهمة
And that connection is change.
باختصار انه التغيير,
In times of change we need
وفي أوقات التغيير نحتاج
new alternatives, new ideas.
الى بدائل وأفكار جديدة.
Now, Brunel worked at the height of the Industrial Revolution,
"برونل" عمل في ذروة الثورة الصناعية
when all of life and our economy
حيث أعيد تشكيل
was being reinvented.
كل حياتنا ومفاهيمنا الأقتصادية.
Now the industrial systems of Brunel's time have run their course,
أما الان فان النظم الصناعية الاتية من عصر "برونل" قد أصبحت قديمة
and indeed they are part of the problem today.
وهي تشكل جزءا من المشكلة اليوم
But, again, we are in the midst of massive change.
أننا الان في وسط تغيير عميق
And that change is forcing us to question
هذا التغيير يدفعنا الى السؤال
quite fundamental aspects of our society --
عن عدد من المبادىء الأساسية في مجتمعنا
how we keep ourselves healthy, how we govern ourselves,
كيف نحافظ على صحتنا, كيف ننظم حياتنا,
how we educate ourselves, how we keep ourselves secure.
كيف نتثقف, كيف نبقى بأمان
And in these times of change, we need these new choices
وفي أوقات التغيير هذه, نحتاج أن نجدد خياراتنا
because our existing solutions are simply becoming obsolete.
لأن الحلول الموجودة أصبحت بكل بساطة قديمة الطراز.
So why design thinking?
لماذا اذا "التفكير التصميمي"؟
Because it gives us a new way of tackling problems.
لأنه يؤمن لنا أسلوبا جديدأ لحل مشكلاتنا
Instead of defaulting to our normal convergent approach
فبدلا من اللجوء الى الأسلوب العادي الذي يعتمد على تقاطع الأفكار
where we make the best choice out of available alternatives,
حيث نعتمد الخيار الأفضل من مجموعة خيارات متاحة,
it encourages us to take a divergent approach,
"التفكير التصميمي" يشجعنا على أعتماد منهجية متشعبة
to explore new alternatives, new solutions,
لإستكشاف خيارات وحلول جديدة
new ideas that have not existed before.
أفكار جديدة لم تكن موجودة من قبل.
But before we go through that process of divergence,
ولكن وقبل المضي قدما في هذه المنهجية المتشعبة,
there is actually quite an important first step.
هناك في الواقع خطوة أولى مهمة:
And that is, what is the question that we're trying to answer?
وهي تعريف السؤال الذي نحاول الإجابة عليه
What's the design brief?
ما هو ملخص التصميم؟
Now Brunel may have asked a question like this,
ربما "برونل" طرح أسئلة مثل
"How do I take a train from London to New York?"
"كيف أخذ القطار من لندن حتى نيويورك؟"
But what are the kinds of questions that we might ask today?
ولكن ما هي الأسئلة التي يتوجب علينا طرحها الان؟
So these are some that we've been asked to think about recently.
في ما يلي بعض هذه الأسئلة التي طلب منا التفكير بها مؤخرا.
And one in particular, is one that we're working on with the Acumen Fund,
وتحديدا, هناك سؤال نعمل على اجابته بالتعاون مع "أكيومان فاند",
in a project that's been funded by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
في مشروع ممول من مؤسسة بيل وميليندا غيتس.
How might we improve access to safe drinking water
كيف بأمكاننا تحسين الوصول الى مياه شرب نظيفة
for the world's poorest people,
للأشخاص الأكثر فقرا في العالم,
and at the same time stimulate innovation
وبنفس الوقت تحفيز الابداع
amongst local water providers?
لدى مزودي المياه المحليين
So instead of having a bunch of American designers
وبدل أن نستعين بمجموعة كبيرة من الخبراء الأميركيين
come up with new ideas that may or may not have been appropriate,
الذين سيأتون بأفكار جديدة قد تكون أو لا تكون مناسبة,
we took a sort of more open, collaborative and participative approach.
إعتمدنا منهجية أكثر انفتاحا, تعاونية وتشاركا.
We teamed designers and investment experts up with
وألفنا مجموعات من المصممين والمستثمرين
11 water organizations across India.
مع 11 منظمة مائية من جميع أنحاء الهند
And through workshops they developed
وقد طوروا خلال حلقات العمل
innovative new products, services, and business models.
منتجات جديدة, وخدمات, ونماذج عمل مبتكرة.
We hosted a competition
وقد استضفنا المنافسة بين هذه المنظمات
and then funded five of those organizations
ومولنا 5 منها
to develop their ideas.
لتطبيق أفكارهم.
So they developed and iterated these ideas.
هكذا تمكنوا من تطوير وأعداد أفكارهم.
And then IDEO and Acumen spent several weeks working with them
بعدها أمضت "آى.دى.إى.أو" و"أكيومين" عدة أسابيع في العمل معهم
to help design new social marketing campaigns,
للمساعدة في تصميم حملات التسويق الاجتماعي,
community outreach strategies, business models,
استراتيجيات توعية المجتمع, نماذج العمل,
new water vessels for storing water
مستوعبات جديدة للمياه لتخزين المياه
and carts for delivering water.
وخرائط لتوزيع المياه.
Some of those ideas are just getting launched into the market.
بعض هذه الأفكار بدأ أستعمالها
And the same process is just getting underway
ونحاول تطبيق نفس المشروع حاليا,
with NGOs in East Africa.
بالتعاون مع بعض المنظمات غير الحكومية في شرق أفريقيا
So for me, this project shows
بالنسبة لي, ان هذه المشاريع تظهر
kind of how far we can go from
المدى الذي يمكن أن نبلغه
some of those sort of small things
انطلاقا من الأفكار البسيطة
that I was working on
التي كنت أعمل عليها
at the beginning of my career.
في بداية حياتي المهنية.
That by focusing on the needs of humans
ذلك أنه ومن خلال التركيز على احتياجات البشر
and by using prototypes
وإستعمال الأنمذجة
to move ideas along quickly,
لاختبار الأفكار بسرعة
by getting the process out of the hands of designers,
بإبعاد العملية عن أيدى المصممين,
and by getting the active participation of the community,
وعبر الحصول على مشاركة المجتمع الفاعلة
we can tackle bigger and more interesting questions.
بامكاننا معالجة مسائل أكبر وأهم.
And just like Brunel, by focusing on systems,
وتماما كما فعل "برونل", عبر التركيز على النظام ككل,
we can have a bigger impact.
يمكن ان يكون لنا تأثير أكبر.
So that's one thing that we've been working on.
هذا مشروع نعمل عليه,
I'm actually really quite interested, and perhaps more interested
انني مهتم كثيرا .... والى حد كبير
to know what this community thinks we could work on.
بمعرفة رأي هذه الجمعية حول الأفكار التي يمكن أن نعمل عليها معا
What kinds of questions do we think
ما هي نوعية الأسئلة التي نعتقد أن
design thinking could be used to tackle?
"التفكير التصميمي" يمكن أن يستخدم لمعالجتها؟
And if you've got any ideas
واذا كانت لديكم أية أفكار
then feel free, you can post them to Twitter.
بامكانكم مشاركتنا أياها عبر تويتر.
There is a hash tag there that you can use, #CBDQ.
عبر استخدام العنوان: CBDQ#.
And the list looked something like this a little while ago.
لائحة الأقتراحات كانت تبدو هكذا منذ فترة قصيرة.
And of course you can search to find the questions that you're interested in
وبالطبع بامكانكم البحث عن الأسئلة التي تهمكم
by using the same hash code.
عبر استخدام نفس العنوان
So I'd like to believe that design thinking
أود أن نعتقد أن "التفكير التصميمي"
actually can make a difference,
بامكانه أن يحدث فرقا,
that it can help create new ideas
وأن يساهم في ايجاد أفكار جديدة,
and new innovations,
وابداعات جديدة
beyond the latest High Street products.
أكثر افادة من المنتجات التي نظهرها في الشوارع التجارية
To do that I think we have to take a more expansive view of design,
لتحقيق ذلك علينا أن ننظر الى التصميم نظرة واسعة
more like Brunel, less a domain of a professional priesthood.
أقرب الى نظرة برونل, وليس فقط كمجال لطائفة مهنية
And the first step is to start asking the right questions.
والخطوة الأولى هي أن نطرح الأسئلة المناسبة
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)